<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rules of the Englishe sodalitie, of the immaculate conception of the mostglorious [sic] virgin Mary Mother of God in the Englishe colledge of the Society of Iesus in Louaine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72833</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898807</idno>
  <idno type="VID">151078</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240861854</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 16854.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S125121</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99898807e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72833)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1998:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rules of the Englishe sodalitie, of the immaculate conception of the mostglorious [sic] virgin Mary Mother of God in the Englishe colledge of the Society of Iesus in Louaine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henrie Iaey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Mackline :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Jesuits --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151078:1"/>
            <p>RVLES <hi>OF THE ENGLISHE</hi> SODALITIE, of the Immaculate Conception of the most glorious Virgin <hi>MARY</hi> MOTHER OF GOD, <hi>In the Englishe Colledge of the Society of</hi> IESVS In Louaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT MACKLINE,</hi> Printed by Henrie Iaey, 1618.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:151078:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151078:2"/>
            <head>The Common Rules. <hi>FIRST PARTE.</hi> VVhat those of the Sodalitie are to obserue towards themselues.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS <hi>Congregaiiou</hi> or <hi>Sodalitie</hi> being insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted &amp; founded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of the euer B. Virgin Mother of God, &amp; vnder the title of her immaculate <hi>Conception,</hi> Let all admitted thereunto, procure with all diligence to become sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler in the deuotiō of this Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of heauen, &amp; especially of this mysterie of her immaculate <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> which is the roote &amp; origē of all her other admirable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The end of this <hi>Sodalitie</hi> is (by the direction of the Fathers of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151078:3"/>
               <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Iesus,</hi>) first: that euery one therof giue himself with all dilligence, to the helpe &amp; spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all profite of himselfe &amp; of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: secondly that euery one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewise exercise charity in the workes of mercy corporall &amp; spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall towards his neighbours, according to his ability &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity &amp; as occasion shalbe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but aboue all the proper &amp; peculiar exercise to be vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of this <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> is to settle peace amongst enemies or ilwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, &amp; to appease discordes, &amp; quarrels, dissentions &amp; disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes especially betwene Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques of our nation, and as concerning those persons and in those cases wherin it is to be feared some great damage may ensewe: Lett therefore, those of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> cherefully goe about with dexterity and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to vnderstand and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue such chaunces as happen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151078:3"/>where they liue, &amp; make the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> acquainted therewith, to the end they may haue his particuler counsell, and direction, keepinge alwaies in memory these wordes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; <hi>Beats pacifici, quoniam filij Dei vocabuntur,</hi> &amp; that it was the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar office of the sonne of God when he came into this world to make peace betwixt the deuine Maiestie &amp; man, &amp; amongst men themselues. Wherefore those to whome (by the <hi>Sodalitie</hi>) it shal bee geuen in charge to make vnion and peace, let them haue regarde to doe it with great charitye and circunspectiō, to the end the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie be not increased which ordinarily falleth out (if care be not vsed) in this importāt &amp; holy worke: Let them procure like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to haue by them some trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of fraternall loue &amp; charitye, speaking of peace, and concorde with their neighbours; of louinge
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151078:4"/>our enemies; of pardoninge iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp; rendering good for euil to our brethren: And let them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke familiar to themselues some li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely and efficacious reasons to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce men thereunto, whereof they may afterwards in occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; occurrences make vse.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The better to attaine this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> these may be most secure and forcible meanes praier, (especially <hi>mentall) the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentation of Sacraments,</hi> (a thinge so profitable &amp; necessary, to obteine victory of the fleshe worlde and deuill) <hi>diligence in abteininge vertue &amp; Christian perfection, recollection so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metime in spirituall Exercise, Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> especially such as by the Father of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> shalbe iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged most expediēt for the seruice of God, &amp; their owne profite.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All are at least once euery Moneth to <hi>confesse,</hi> &amp; afterwards in their <hi>Oratorie to cōmunicate</hi> euery first Sunday in the Moneth, &amp; on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151078:4"/>al the principall feasts of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi> &amp; the <hi>B. Virgen,</hi> on the feaste of <hi>All Saints,</hi> and of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> It is left notwith standinge free to euery one to doe it more often for his greater profite, &amp; the greater edification of others, as true mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this <hi>Sodalitie;</hi> And as it is lawfull for euery one to chuse for his <hi>Confessor</hi> him who may be for his greater content, so it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise conuenient, that he haue one certeine, &amp; ordinary.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Euery one shall spend a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of on hower in <hi>Mentall prayer</hi> euery day in the morning, so soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne as he riseth, (for that this time is better &amp; more certeine) or the eueninge before supper, or some other time which shalbe must conuenient, taking for his <hi>Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō</hi> some pointe of the life or passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> chiefly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the order of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie:</hi> And for this ende it willbe meete, that euery one haue some
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151078:5"/>spiritual booke of meditations, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for his vse those poinctes, which the Father of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> or his <hi>Confessour</hi> shal iudge fittest for his greater profite.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Euery one shal say euery day seuen <hi>Paters</hi> &amp; as many <hi>Aues</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the 7. ioyes of our <hi>B. Ladij,</hi> that she may obteyne for vs the 7. gistes of the H. Ghoste, &amp; his holy grace; hee shal also pray for his owne saluation, the helpe of sinners, the Exaltation of the holy Churche, the increase of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> for those which are in mortall sinne, or in dissention, &amp; for the soules of the faithfull departed. On Saterday they shal say moreouer the hymne <hi>O gloriosa Domina</hi> with the versicles, &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Conception: And all are to knowe, that by sayinge these 7. <hi>Pater nosters,</hi> and 7. <hi>Aues</hi> in some Church of the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Iesus,</hi> or in some other, (where there are no Churches of the said Societie;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151078:5"/>they gaine all the <hi>Indulgences</hi> that on those dayes are to be gayned in any Churche, either within or without the wals of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. All are to heare <hi>Masse,</hi> as neere as they can, euery day (though it be not a holie daie) for it is a thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge verie fruitfull; But when by reason of some necessitie, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of moment they cannot doe it, let thē in place of hearinge <hi>Masse</hi> performe some other deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; And while they heare <hi>Masse,</hi> let them obsteine from talkinge with others, &amp; procure to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, with much reuerence, both interriour &amp; exteriour: Let them alsoe frequente sermons, diuine office, and often visite ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Let euery one accustome him self, to make euery eueninge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goe to reste, the <hi>Examen of conscience,</hi> according to those fiue pointes conteyned in the forme of the general <hi>Examen,</hi> for which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151078:6"/>ende it is conuenient that each haue one by him ether printed or written.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Euery one according to the direction of his <hi>Confessour,</hi> or of the Father of the <hi>Congregation</hi> (with whome for this purpose it wilbe conuenient sometimes to deale, &amp; treate familiarly out of the times of <hi>Congregation</hi>) must attende to the mortification of his passion, especially of those with which he is ordinarily molested, to which, will greatly helpe the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler Examen,</hi> ordeyned for the rootinge out of vices &amp; defectes, as the said Father shall further in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>structe him.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Let euery one afforde some tyme for the readinge of <hi>spirituall Bookes,</hi> the which is a great fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to prayer, and of great helpe in all other vertuous exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises: And it willbe conuenient that euery one aske the iudgemēt of the Father or his <hi>Confessour</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151078:6"/>the choyse of bookes most agreeable to his particuler defects.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Let them procure often to deale with the Father of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> of the means to atteyne vertue, and the wayes to knowe the temptations of our ghostly enemy for their defence, &amp; victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ouer them, for which purpose it wil auayle much to make choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of some particuler faste in the weeke (besides those of obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) or some other sorte of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>THE SECOND PARTE. <hi>VVhat those of the Sodalitie are to obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue towards their Superiours.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">12.</head>
            <p>THey ought in generall &amp; in particuler to honour, &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Father of the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as their common Father, may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151078:7"/>dispense with the Rules, custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; ordinances, when, &amp; as far forth as he shall iudge expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. Wherefore it is conueniēt nothinge of moment be handled in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> without his knowledge, &amp; consent.</p>
            <p n="13">13. They shall honour also and beare all respecte to the <hi>Prefect</hi> of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> whome, as the head thereof all must promptly obey in thinges belonginge to the seruice of God, and good of the <hi>Congregation.</hi> They shall not bee wantinge also to honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect the 2. <hi>assistants,</hi> as chief next to the prefect and allotted to him for his aide and assistance in the gouernement, which they shall likewise performe towards all the rest of the <hi>Officers</hi> in thinges belonginge to their offices.</p>
            <p n="14">14. All must accepte with due promptnes &amp; humilitie the <hi>penaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> &amp; mortifications which shalbe enioyned them, be they for their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151078:7"/>defectes or exercise of vertue and shall fullfill the same she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing desire of amendment: Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewise when they shalbe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, or corrected by the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> they most heare it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, &amp; humbly.</p>
            <p n="15">15. When to any one shalbe assigned any office, or a busines geuen in charge by the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> or from the <hi>Congregation,</hi> he is to accept it with all charity, &amp; readines, and without excuse, procuringe the execution thereof with conuenient diligence. And if after mature consideration the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, some difficultie should oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr, let him presente the same in priuate, to the end better deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration may be taken.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>THE THIRD PART. <hi>VVhat those of the Sedalitie are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue towards one another.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151078:8"/>
            <head type="sub">16.</head>
            <p>LEt them procure to loue each other with true, and syncere affection, &amp; so maynteine peace amongst thēselues, &amp; with others, &amp; to remayne vnited each to the other with that stricte bond of charity, which beseemeth true children of the most <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> &amp; members of such a <hi>Congregation,</hi> flyinge the least occasion of disu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: And when by frailtie any thinge should fall out betwene them contrary to this holy Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the <hi>Congregatiō,</hi> whosoeuer shall come to knowe it, he must spedily giue notice to the <hi>Father,</hi> that as soone as may be, he proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de meete &amp; conuenient remedie.</p>
            <p n="17">17. When any difference, or sute for interest of goods, or other like causes should happē amongst those of the <hi>Sodality,</hi> let it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured with fraternall charitye by meanes of the <hi>Father</hi> &amp; <hi>Prefect,</hi> that by way of agreement, or compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151078:8"/>it be ended with all speede, &amp; loue possible.</p>
            <p n="18">18. When any of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> shall fall in to sicknes, or other missortune of moment, care must be had that the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> be warned as soone as may be, to the end they giue order he be visited, ayded, &amp; comforted by others of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> with such chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table offices as are conuenient; And he to whome it appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth may warne &amp; appointe the rest such praiers as are to be made for his necessitie both corporall &amp; spirituall.</p>
            <p n="19">19. When any of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> shall <hi>departe this life,</hi> euery <hi>Priest</hi> of the <hi>Congregation</hi> shall say for his soule a Masse, the day of his death or when he hath first notice the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof (if it be possible) or as soone as may be, and the rest (as soone as they can) must procure a Masse for him, &amp; that (if it may be) at some priuiledged <hi>Altar,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151078:9"/>the Indulgences, of beades graines, medalls, &amp; the like graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the diliuery of soules out of purgatory. Moreouer in their <hi>Oratorie,</hi> after a Masse of <hi>Requiem,</hi> they are to say together the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>Office of the dead.</hi> Besides for one whole Moneth those of the <hi>Soda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> must say euery day a <hi>De profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> for the soule departed with the prayer for the dead, &amp; 3. <hi>Paters</hi> &amp; 3. <hi>Aues.</hi> But from these suffrages are to be excluded such as for beinge absent without leaue at the times appointed are not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the table of those who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente, as also those, whose far distance wholy excusinge them to frequente shall not for the spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of two yeares haue written to the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> with shewe of este<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; accounte held therof. Besi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des lett euery one remember to recommend in generall to our Lord in their prayers the soules of all the <hi>Sodalitye</hi> departed.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151078:9"/> 20. When <hi>suffrages</hi> are to be geuē or consultation to be helde, or treatie to be made, for the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge of any into the <hi>Congregation,</hi> or for the election of <hi>Prefecte, assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, Consultors,</hi> or other officers, or busenes of that nature which require voyce, or consultation, Let euery one procure to procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de without humane respect, with all freedome &amp; synceritye of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, choosinge alwaies them, whome in their conscience they shall iudge meete for the purpose, hauinge only regard to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honour of God and common good of the <hi>Sodalitie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>THE FOVRTH PARTE. <hi>VVhat those of the Sodalitie are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue towards their neighbours.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">21.</head>
            <p>LEt them flie not only all ill <hi>Company</hi> &amp; all manner of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151078:10"/>which may bringe perill to their soules, as gaminge, and dissolute places, procuringe to conuerse often, and for the most parte, with such as may be a helpe vnto them by their good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, keepinge themselues free from all vnbeseeminge speaches, from scandalous murmuringes, &amp; other inconueniences, the which (besides the offence of God) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minishe the good name, &amp; credite of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> &amp; the fame of their neighbours; But let them also endeuour to be very exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar in their words, life, &amp; actions to the edification of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, &amp; with all not to be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with charitable counsailes to exhorte them to vertue, and integrity of life, frequentinge of the Sacramentes, to meditation, &amp; mental prayer, exercises so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the good of soules: And finally lett them imploye them themselues willingly in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151078:10"/>&amp; healpe of their said neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours aswel tēporall as spirituall. 22. These of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> must not onelie be content to knowe well themselues the Christian doctrine, or catechisme, but they must also procure that all their familie likewise knowe the same, aswell their childerē &amp; kindred, as also their seruauntes, &amp; such as dwel with them, to whome they mufl afforde a conuenient ime to learne it, and to satisfie all other obligations of christian dutie; As to heare <hi>Masse</hi> euery Sonday and holie daie; To confesse and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate at their appointed times exhortinge them to doe it many times in the yeare, &amp; likewise to obserue all the commaundemēts of God, &amp; of the Holy Churche, prouidinge in the best manner possible, that in their house his diuine Maiestie be not offended, nor yet that there be any occasion thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151078:11"/>
            <head>THE FIFTE PART. <hi>VVhat they are to obserue towards the Sodality it self.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">23.</head>
            <p>ALl must be dilligent in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge to the <hi>Congregation,</hi> or <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> on those dayes on which it is held, that is euery Saterday, &amp; Sonday, and all the Feastes of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> his glorious <hi>Mother,</hi> (of precepte) on the day of all Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, &amp; the feastes of the Apostles, which lighte vpon wensday. And let them performe with attention &amp; denotion, the exercises of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, &amp; mentall prayer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, discourses, &amp; other accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed exercises of the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as the Father shall iudge the qualitie, &amp; comoditie of time, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sines, occasions, &amp; particular nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the <hi>Congregation</hi> to require.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Let euery one with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence endeuour to come in due
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151078:11"/>time to the <hi>Congregation,</hi> layinge aside all busines for the honour of God &amp; his most glorious Mother, notwith standinge if any iust im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment shall happen to any, let him aduertise the Father, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte, &amp; fayling herein lett him supplye it in the first <hi>Congregation</hi> followinge.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Although the mortificatiōs, penaunces, &amp; other like secrets of the <hi>Congregation</hi> ought to remaine priuate amongst those only that be of it (vnles some one were to be enformed thereof, the which should truly pretend, and were readie to enter) notwithstāding it is not forbidden by this, to let anie one leade to the <hi>Congregation</hi> some frende which is not of it, to moue him with that good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to enter therein, so it be done with licence of the Father or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte; but at such times it is better to refraine from geuinge of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, or mortifications to any,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151078:12"/>who should not of himself de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde them.</p>
            <p n="26">26. As for their places in the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> regarde is not to be had to any sorte of precedencie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the oratory it self, nor in goinge out thereof, to auoyde all ceremonies, &amp; ambition; And in their departure, let them vse such modestie &amp; composition, in their gate, in their speache, and all the rest of their actions, that euery one may reape good example thereby &amp; take notie of the profite made by their spirituall exercise of the <hi>Sodality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. Seeing those of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> come together purposely, to make some recollection, &amp; seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster themselues for an hower &amp; a half from worldly affaires, the better to vnite them selues with God, they must keepe continuall silence in their Oratory, euery one attendinge to him self, &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stayninge from talkinge with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151078:12"/>others, euen of spirituall thinges, much more of worldly, curious, &amp; vaine matters.</p>
            <p n="28">28. When Conference is made of spirituall matters, or other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires are treated, let those of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> expecte till they be askt, neither propoundinge, nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweringe (if they be not demaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) either in generall, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Yf notwithstandinge any one of them for iust causes would speake or propounde any thinge to the <hi>Congregation</hi> publiquely, lett him not doe it, without first ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing asked licence of the Father: And let them beware, in deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe their opinions, to dispute &amp; impugne, the sayinges of others or to contende: But if in any thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, one should be of contrary iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement to an other, and it should seeme good to declare it, let him bringe his reasons with modestie, and charitye, and with an intente that truthe may haue place, &amp; that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151078:13"/>that may be done which is beste, slyinge all shewe of desire to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come superiour in his owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p n="29">29. When any is to goe out of the Citty some long voyage, or to remayne abroade some long time let him acquainte the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Presect,</hi> &amp; at due time lett him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, or procure, that licence may publiquely be asked in his behalf in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> and let him take his patent of the Prefecte &amp; of the Assistantes, that he may be admitted in other Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; also to the ende that when he returneth, he may be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, &amp; accepted of, in this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> without further testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Let him procure also in the place of his abode, to obserue (as much as is possible) the Rules of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> &amp; performe the exercises thereof, in particuler, their mentall prayer, examinatiō of conscience, pursute of vertue,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151078:13"/>frequentinge of the Sacraments, &amp; exampie of good life, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe them selues also in some workes proper to the <hi>Congregation,</hi> as in peace-makinge or other workes of mercie, and helpe of their neighbours. Let him remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber also to pray often for the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall aduauncemēt, &amp; good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse of the <hi>Sodalitie:</hi> as the <hi>Soda</hi>-litie is in like manner to pray for him; And if he is to be longe absent, let him nowe and then giue accompte of himself by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Congregation;</hi> And this at leaste once euery half yeare.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Whilest those of the <hi>Sodali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> are meetinge together in the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> one of the <hi>Lectors</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted shal reade some spirituall boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke assigned by the Father: The sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is to be done, whilest vpon any occasion stay is made of any of the ordinary exercises.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Those that shal make instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to be admitted into the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151078:14"/>let them doe it by way of memorial: They must be syncere Catholikes resolued to liue well, &amp; endewed with other particuler qualites which by the <hi>Congregatiō</hi> are lefte to the discretion of the Father: and if they be such, as are not fully knowne (at least) by some of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> or some of the Fathers of the <hi>Societie,</hi> let it be cōmitted to one or two of the <hi>Congregation</hi> (acordinge as it shall seeme best to the secret consult) that they take certeine informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether such qualities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, as are requisite, which beinge founde wantinge, they are in good manner to be put of, but if they shalbe iudged fit by the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalitie,</hi> then they are to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their probatiō. Before their admittance, all are to make a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Confession</hi> of their whole life, with whome they haue most deuotiū: And if already they haue made one a litle before, it is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151078:14"/>to make another, beginnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge from their last, &amp; it would be very profitable vnto them, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke for some dayes the spirituall Exercises of the <hi>Societie of Iesus,</hi> instituted by Blessed Father <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> founder of the same (if so be, they feele them selues inclined thereunto) furthermore, before they be admitted, lett them haue frequented the <hi>Congregation</hi> (at the least for 3. monethes, so farre forth as their occasiōs permitt) &amp; be well informed, &amp; instructed of those thinges which are obserued therein, they are to see these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Rules to the end they may consider them well, and resolue them selues, if they can, and will fullfill what is conteyned in the, whereof one, or both of the Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes, some Counsultour, or some other deputed by the secret <hi>Congregation</hi> shall haue care: After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when they are to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, their Instructours must
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151078:15"/>first in their absence make that full &amp; ample relation, of which is treated in the particuler Rules of the Instructours. And beinge to proceede to the acte of admission let it be done with the consente of the greater parte of those, that are present in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> by secret suffrages, and in absence of them of whose admittance they treate, &amp; beinge accepted of, then they shalbe brought in afterwards at the first ensewinge <hi>Congregation.</hi> Finally, All are to haue these Rules, that nowe, and then, they may renewe, and refreshe the memory of them; And they must be read in full <hi>Congregation</hi> at the first oportunitie after the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe of newe officers. And as it is not intended that any who shall fayle in the obseruance of them, should incurre any sorte of sinne (euen veniall) so by obseruinge them, (besides that he shall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne most efficacions helpe to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151078:15"/>true spirituall life) he shal more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer gayne very great, &amp; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler merite in the sighte of God, &amp; his most glorious Mother; To whome be geuen glory, &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>Particuler Rules <hi>For the Officers of the</hi> Congregatiō. Rules belonginge to the Prefect.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Prefect,</hi> as he excelleth the rest in degree, &amp; office, so he ought to endeuour to excell them in vertue, &amp; exact obseruance of al the Rules.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let him embrace the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement with great charitie, and procure to applye himself with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151078:16"/>all diligence thereunto, as a thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of great importance for the seruice of God, &amp; the most <hi>Blessed Virgin;</hi> And let him be carefull to come alwaies in time, as well to geue good example, as to prouide for all thinges, which (by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the assistants) shall seeme necessary for the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He is to consulte with the <hi>Eather</hi> of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> &amp; with his Assistants (before he ordeyne any thinge) all the particuler thinges which shall occurre in the gouernement of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> either belonginge to the spirituall profite of those of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> or any other matter; And therefore euery Saterday, or Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day (in fit place) he shall treate with them, &amp; for that purpose he shall haue a booke, in which he shall distinctly note (for his better memory) al that which he is to consult or ordeyne.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When there occurreth some
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151078:16"/>weightie matter, (for which greater consideration is required, &amp; therefore it may seeme neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to haue the aduice of many) he may (if it seeme good to the Father) call (besides the two Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes) the Consultours, with whome also euery first Saterday of the Moneth he shall treate, howe those of the <hi>Congregation</hi> doe procede, howe the Rules be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, And whether there be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie to make any ordinance for the good of the <hi>Sodalitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. When any one is receaued into the <hi>Congregation</hi> let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently procure that the booke of Rules be geuen him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When he shall vnderstand that any of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> is sicke, he shall cause him to be visited, as it shall seeme most conuenient, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiringe afterwards the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the sick person, procuringe also that to be performed for his tēporall &amp; spirituall helpe which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151078:17"/>is conteyned in the 18. common Rule.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When any of the <hi>Congregation</hi> shall die, he shall haue care that (as soone as may be) the ordinary obligatiōs be performed for him, according to the 19. cōmon Rule: And when the deceased person shall leaue behinde him Childrē, poore, and in necessitie, he shall procure that a consulte be made in presence of the Father, with the Assistantes, and Consultours, howe to succour them accordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to their necessity &amp; qualitie, &amp; abilitie of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. When any ordinances are to be made, either by way of decree in writtinge, or in other manner, he shall procure with the Father, &amp; assistantes, that the secret <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> be assebled, in the which they shall deliberate &amp; decree so much as is expediente, &amp; beeinge thinges fit to be published, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the generall <hi>Congregatiō,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151078:17"/>the deliberation, or decree made in the secret, shalbe proposed in the generall, to the ende, that (by Gods grace) that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed may be better obserued.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It doth belonge to the <hi>Prefecte</hi> (if he happen to be a Prieste) to say before the <hi>Congregation,</hi> the accustomed praiers &amp; letanies of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> the Prayer <hi>Actiones no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stras</hi> &amp;c. before meditation, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation ended, to intone, the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat,</hi> and after, say the prayer <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulis tùis &amp;c.</hi> &amp; at the ende of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> to beginne, &amp; prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute together the <hi>Salue Regina,</hi> or <hi>Alma Redemptoris,</hi> or <hi>Aue Regina coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> or <hi>Regina coeli,</hi> with the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicle, and prayer for the time: As also to beginne the Prayers, hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Psalmes, &amp; say all the prayers, &amp; letanies, which are accostomed to be said at the distribution of <hi>Sainctes,</hi> before, &amp; after admissions, before, &amp; after the priuate <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> &amp; to doe the office, in sayin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151078:18"/>the prayers when the office of the dead shalbe recited, &amp; perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the office in the Mattens, of <hi>tenebras,</hi> and in the houres of the three dayes of the holy weeke: To performe the office in the Vespers of the Eue of the Conception: All which offices ought to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him with the Rochet, (yf he be a Prelate) Therefore, it is conuenient, that he prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in due time for all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said actions, and other such like, perusinge before, all the thinges which belonge vnto him to say, &amp; doe, that he may perfectly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his office in the sighte of all the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>Rules of the two Assistantes.</head>
            <head>1.</head>
            <p>THe office of the 2. <hi>Assistantes,</hi> is, to assiste the <hi>Prefect,</hi> and helpe him in the gouernement of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151078:18"/>the <hi>Congregation,</hi> &amp; therefore they ought to sit neere vnto him, (that is) the first, on the righte hand, &amp; the secōd on the lefte: And when the <hi>Prefecte</hi> is absent, the first <hi>Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant</hi> must supplie his place in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement; And the first <hi>Assistant</hi> also beinge absente, the second shall supplie; In which cases they shall haue the same authoritie, &amp; the same obligatiō to obserue the Rules of the <hi>Prefecte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let them procure to be very exemplar in vertue, &amp; exact in the obseruance of all the Rules.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Assistants</hi> ought particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to affecte, &amp; seeke the good gouernement of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> &amp; be diligente in cominge to the same, for the example of the rest, and helpe of the <hi>Prefect</hi> in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that shall occurre.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When they deliuer ther opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, they shall doe it with all modesty, &amp; without passion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing regard to the seruice of God,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151078:19"/>&amp; the most <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> &amp; to the good of the <hi>Sodality:</hi> and what shalbe treated with the <hi>Prefect,</hi> or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, they shall keepe in secret, as well from strangers, as from those of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> it beinge the office of the <hi>Prefect</hi> to publishe (when it salbe necessary) the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations, and other thinges which shalbe done. And if in their resolutions, there happen diuersitie of opinions betwene the <hi>Assistants</hi> &amp; the <hi>Prefecte,</hi> let it be signified vnto the Father, that he may prouide as shalbe expedient.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Let them knowe that of thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues they cannot ordeyne any thinge, and when it shall occurre vnto them, to propose some thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge for the furtheringe of the rest in spirite, or for the helpe of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> or of the workes which it hath embraced, they may represent it vnto the Father, or to the <hi>Prefecte,</hi> remittinge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnto them (after they haue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151078:19"/>proposed it) in all that shalbe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in our Lord.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Assistants</hi> also ought to put the <hi>Prefecte</hi> in minde of thinges concerninge the gouernement of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And bycause the <hi>Assistants</hi> are likewise accoustomed to giue <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structours,</hi> to those that desire to be admitted into the <hi>Congregatiō,</hi> they must obserue that which is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned in the 6. Rule of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultours,</hi> &amp; more amplie in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the <hi>Instructours.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>Rules of the Secretarie of the Congregation.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Secretarie</hi> must be present at all the actions of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> as well publique, as priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, he shall write in a booke (ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpose) the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that shalbe done: He shall haue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151078:20"/>a Cheste, or deske locked with a key, where he shall lay vp all the thinges of his office well kept, &amp; in good order, that they may easily befounde whē soeuer there shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be neede, &amp; that afterwards he may resigne them vnto his suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessour: he must also be mindfull of due secrecie; wherefore he shall not talke with any of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges determined, or to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> nor shewe any writinge, without order, or knowledge of the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefecte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He shall haue two other boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, one litle, &amp; the other greater, the lesse shall serue to note the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, surnames, countrey, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of those that shalbe admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the <hi>Congregation,</hi> as well after three monethes probation, as by vertue of patentes, or other certeine testimonies wich come from forraine <hi>Congregations,</hi> and therin he shall note the day of his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151078:20"/>admission: And that little booke shal serue, that after a yeare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, they may take out of it, and transferre into the greater booke the names, surnames, countreyes, profession, and day of admission of those, which for that yeare haue diligently fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented the <hi>Congregation</hi> as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth; and in the same great booke he shall keepe, an accounte of those that chaunge their sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Moreouer, he shall haue a litle booke in which he shall note those that departe, especially who are not likely to returne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He shall write those letters which occurre to be written in the name of the <hi>Congregatiō,</hi> &amp; shall geue Patentes to those that take any iourney, sealinge the one &amp; the other with the accustomed seale of the <hi>Congregation</hi> (all not withstanding by order of the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Presect</hi>) And he shall alwaies haue a Register of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151078:21"/>thinges of momente, especially of the decrees which shalbe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de; of the Patentes which are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to such as departe; &amp; of those who shalbe brought from other <hi>Congregations,</hi> and of theire accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He shall haue an vnder-se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie which may helpe him to write, &amp; in his absence assiste in his place; but that vnder <hi>Secretary</hi> must not be present at the consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, vnles sometime it seeme otherwise expedient to the <hi>Father</hi> &amp; <hi>Prefect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. He shall haue care that in the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> at the entrance of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, on one fide, there be a table with the names &amp; surnames of all of the <hi>Congregaiion</hi> (yet liuinge) &amp; on the other side another table of the names, and surnames of those that frequente the <hi>Congregation,</hi> &amp; neere vnto that, another of those that frequente (which are not Priestes) that they may signe them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151078:21"/>that are to communicate. And also let there be in the oratorie, or in some other fit, and conuenient place, the <hi>Bull of the erection of the Congregation,</hi> the common <hi>Rules, a sumne of the Indulgences,</hi> and other thinges as shalbe ordeyned by the <hi>Father</hi> &amp; <hi>Prefect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. He shall haue a care to reade, or see read euery Saterday, the plenary &amp; other notable <hi>Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which in the weeke follow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge may be gayned by those of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> and also in due times the Rules, and all other thinges which shall occurre to be read in the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. It shal be also his care to call those of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> one by one, by name, &amp; surname to goe and take the suffrages, when they shalbe distributed, &amp; to call also in Sundayes <hi>Congregations</hi> by name, and surname, those, that are that weeke to visite the <hi>Hospitall</hi> (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided that they be of those then
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151078:22"/>present at the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Likewise he shall haue care to make a bill of those which shal make their houre of prayer in the <hi>quarant-houer,</hi> hauing regarde that the houres lesse commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous be assigned to those that dwel not so farr of: And it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the said bill be fastned in the <hi>Oratorie</hi> (at the least) the morninge of the day goinge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</p>
            <p n="9">9 He shall doe diuers other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which occurrēces of actions shal declare to belōge to his office, &amp; which also shalbe assigned vnto him by the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefecte.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>Rules of the Consultours of the Congregation.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>THe office of the <hi>Consultours,</hi> is to ayde with their counsaile, &amp; helpe the <hi>Prefect</hi> in his charge,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151078:22"/>for which it is expediēt that they be very zealous in the seruice of our Lorde, &amp; of the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> and of the good progresse, &amp; spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all helpe of the <hi>Congregation:</hi> They must also be well vnited with the <hi>Prefect,</hi> &amp; amongst them selues, in fraternall charitie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They shall procure in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges belōginge to the <hi>Congregatiō,</hi> &amp; in the obseruāce of their Rules, to be the first, that the others moued by their exāple be more diligēte. 3. When soeuer the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> shall call them to consulte, they must shewe thēselues readie, &amp; deliuer plainely, ther opinions, and when there shalbe variance, euery one must tell his reasons, without touchinge, or reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge others, &amp; if they goe about to confute the reasons of others, they must doe it in such manner, that they giue no signes of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictiō, but only to confirme that which they iudge conuenient.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:151078:23"/> 4 If some thinge occurre to any of them, profitable for the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall good of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> he may propounde it priuately vnto the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> remittinge himself afterwards to that which they shall determine.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are also to haue care to keepe secret that which is treated in the Consultes, not only from others, but also from them of the <hi>Congregation</hi> it self.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When there shalbe assgned vnto them by the officers &amp; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultour,</hi> any of those who demaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de entrance into the <hi>Congregation,</hi> to be instructed, they must haue particuler care to instructe, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte them well in thinges con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the said <hi>Congregation,</hi> and let them reuiewe diligently, the particuler Rules of the <hi>Instructours,</hi> procuringe to obserue them pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151078:23"/>
            <head>The Rules of the Instructours of those which desire to enter into the Sodalitie.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>WHen the <hi>Father</hi> shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to any the memoriall of some persō (not knowne) who desireth to enter into the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> they must with all diligence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themselues of his qualitie, &amp; geue accounte of their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation with all speede, vnto the <hi>Congregation,</hi> that it may quickly be resolued, whether he is to be proposed or no, to the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> for his admittance to probation; and to this end let them reade what is conteyned in the 31. common Rule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After any shalbe admitted to the said <hi>Probation,</hi> the <hi>Instructours</hi> must see that duringe the time thereof, they fullfill what soeuer
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151078:24"/>is prescribed in the forenamed 31 common Rules, which treateth particulerly hereof, especially about the generall Confession, in that manner, which in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Rule is declared.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They must shewe them all the common &amp; particuler Rules, with the customes of the <hi>Sodalitie.</hi> which often they must inculcate, declaringe vnto them that which they doe not well vnderstad, that they may resolue whether they can, and will obserue them. And to be briefe, they must instructe them of what soeuer they are to doe, as well duringe the time of their Probation, as after their admission.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It apparteyneth also to their care, to instructe them exactly, in that which they are to doe on the day of their admittance, and on the day whē they are publiquely to be brought in into the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> which shalbe the first day of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151078:24"/>
               <hi>Congregation,</hi> after the day of their admittance, for which ende it behooueth the <hi>Instructours,</hi> &amp; the persons instructed, to peruse dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the forenamed 31 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Rule.</p>
            <p n="5">5 They must endeuour that those who me they instructe, be taught the maner of cōmendinge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to God, euery morninge, to examine their consciences at night, as also to pray mentally, &amp; to liue like good Christians.</p>
            <p n="6">6 They must haue care to warne the <hi>Father</hi> &amp; the <hi>Prefect,</hi> when the time of their probatiō is expired. 7. That, which by all meanes the <hi>Instructour</hi> is to obserue, when the partie by him instructed is to be admitted, (that those of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> may with a safe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science geue their voyce) is, as followeth, first he must admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe the partie (to be admitted) to goe out of the <hi>Oratorit</hi> Secondly, he shall with a loude voyce say,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151078:25"/>howe such an one (tellinge name, surname, countrey, state and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession) was so long since admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the secret <hi>Congregation,</hi> to his probation, and that he was assigned for his <hi>Instructour:</hi> That he hath endeuoured to instructe him according to the Rules of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> as well as he could: That the three monethes of probation are expired: That he hath made a generall Confessiō of his whole life, or from his last generall, of which he hath sufficiently cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified the <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Sodalitie:</hi> howe he himself hath obserued, that the said partie hath, duringe the terme of the three monethes (when he was not laufully hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred) not only frequented dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> but also the holy Sacraments: That he hath shewed a good &amp; christian spirite: That he seemeth to him suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently instructed in the Rules of the <hi>Sodalitte,</hi> &amp; in what else so euer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151078:25"/>a good menber of the same is bounde to obserue. That he she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth a good and resolute will, to put them in execution: That he show a purpose, at tymes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to frequent the <hi>Sodalitie:</hi> And that for all the respectes afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resaid, he doe verily iudge him worthie to be admitted into the same and hopeth it wil haue good successe. Thirdly, after that by suffrages he shall be admitted, the <hi>Instructour</hi> must aduertise him, that the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> hath receaued him: that the next <hi>Congregatiō,</hi> he is to be brought in, after the accustomed manner set downe in the Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes; That cōmunicatinge on the day of his entrance, at the Masse of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> either first, or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde, he gayneth a plenary <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</hi> Fourthly, in the next <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalitie,</hi> at the end of the meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he shall cause the partie, to goe out againe of the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> and shall put the <hi>Father</hi> in minde of his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151078:26"/>entrance to be reade, &amp; the <hi>Father</hi> geuing him order so to doe, he shall goe out to bringe him in; And at the doore the <hi>Sacristans</hi> shall receaue him, accomponie &amp; directe him in the rest of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; ceremonies accustomed in such times, as is set downe in the sixte rule of the <hi>Sacristans,</hi> and in the foresaid chapter of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>Rules of the Sacristans of the Sodalitie.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Sacristans</hi> are to haue care of the <hi>Chappell,</hi> &amp; of all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges perteyninge to the vse the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof and therefore they must al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies come the first, (at least half an hower) before the time of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> to prepare all thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for Masse.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151078:26"/> 2. They shall haue care to dresse the Altar with ornamentes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the times both festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall and feriall withsuche other offices, and functions as are to be done, dispatchinge all eyther the day before, or when else wilbe more commodious for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Eight dayes before the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall communion, at the end of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> they shall admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe all, eyther by themselues, or by meanes of the <hi>Father,</hi> that the next Sundy wilbe the first of the moneth, that they may prepare themselues to commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They shall also haue care to prepare the <hi>suffrages</hi> of the <hi>Sainctes,</hi> euery moneth, and to haue them ready, to be deuided the Sater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes <hi>Congregation,</hi> next before the beginninge of the newe mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It belonges also to their charge, to prouide all thinges
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151078:27"/>necessary for the geuinge of voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whensoeuer, either for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, election of <hi>Officers,</hi> or any other busines of like nature is to be done, and they must goe about with the thinges, prouided for that purpose.</p>
            <p n="6">6 It is their office also to receaue at the doore, and leade betwene them the <hi>newe admitted</hi> to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of prayer before the Altar, and to accompany them to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strats benche, to be embraced, accordinge to the custome.</p>
            <p n="7">7 They shall also haue the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to aduertise timely those, which are to reade the <hi>Lessons</hi> in all the offices which in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> are to be said, leadinge them to the deske, and to bringe them back againe (betweene thē) to their places, obseruinge parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly what is set downe in the sixte chapter, of the custome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge the diuine office.</p>
            <p n="8">8. They must haue a diligent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151078:27"/>care timely to hange vp at the <hi>Oratory</hi> doore, the table with the names &amp; surnames of thē which are not Priestes that will receiue at the first Masse, remembringe, that when they put the Pixe with hostes vpon the Altar, for the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertorie, that they put so many hostes as there are names signed, and so manie more as they may probably gesse will come persons to communitate after the offerto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, putting rather alwaies to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny then to fewe: And the same is to be obserued for the communiō in the second Masse after the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</hi> Likewise euery day of communion (as well generall, as particuler) to make a bill of all them that doe communicate, and to giue it to the <hi>Father,</hi> at the end of the moneth,</p>
            <p n="9">9. They must prepare the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles</hi> for Candelmas day, the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> for Palme Sunday, in due time.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151078:28"/> 10. They must admonishe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Presecte,</hi> of what soeuer wanteth in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cristie,</hi> that it maybe prouided, &amp; must haue a booke, to write the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein what soeuer is laid out: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther must they lay out any thinge, much or litle, for the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> without first acquaintinge the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or <hi>Prefect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 They must keepe a booke, wherein they shall make a very exact, &amp; faithfull Inuētorie of all thinges belōging to the <hi>Oratory</hi> (be they neuer so litle) &amp; when soeuer newe <hi>Sacristans</hi> shall succeede, &amp; the olde goe out, they must all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with two others (assigned by the <hi>Father,</hi> &amp; <hi>Prefect</hi>) reuewe the said Inuentorie, adioyning thereunto What soeuer hath bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne made, or geuen, or come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of newe, for the seruice of the <hi>Chappel,</hi> or vse of the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> (which is not already writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151078:28"/>
            <head>Rules of the Treasourer.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Treasourers</hi> office is, to kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe the money which they of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> shall offer for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities thereof, &amp; which by any other meanes shall come to the <hi>Congregation,</hi> and to geue it out to those persons, which the <hi>Prefect</hi> shall appointe in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and forme, as the rule pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He must keepe a booke of what he receaues, and layes out, And as concerninge what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, he must note with the greatest distinction, and perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitie possible, all the sommes which he receaues, specifyinge the causes, and the dayes, &amp; with the same diligence, he must note what soeuer is layd out, specifyin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge also the causes, dayes, and the order geuen.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151078:29"/> 3. He must also exacte of euery one what they are to geue for the ordinary expences of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiion;</hi> And he must so distinctly put it downe in writinge, that it may be cleerely seene howe much euery one hath geuen, and what he is yet to geue, that so he may sometimes remember them, &amp; exacte it of them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the expences to be made for the vse of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> he must not geue any mony to what persons soeuer, without or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the <hi>Prefect</hi> in Writinge.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When the <hi>Treasourer</hi> shall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mony to any one, to be spente in small matters for the <hi>Oratories</hi> vse, as to <hi>Sacrictans,</hi> or other such like, let him note it particularly, in the booke of expences, to the end, that those which haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the money, may render their accounte of the small expences, &amp; geue a bill thereof to the <hi>Prefecte,</hi> who must reuiewe it, to the end,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151078:29"/>that what soeuer they shall haue laid out (besides) of their owne, may be restored vnto them, or not hauing laid out all, it may ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue for the next expences they are to make, which bills (for good order sake, after the <hi>Prefect</hi> hath seene them) are to begeuen to the <hi>Secretarie,</hi> to keepe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Euery 2. monethes, the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sourer</hi> is to geue vnto the <hi>Prefect,</hi> a distincte accounte of the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the receiptes, &amp; expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which afterwards is to be geuen to the <hi>Secretarie</hi> to keepe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>The Rules of the Porters.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>THey must come (the first) to open the <hi>Oratory</hi> doore, &amp; to see it be swept, handsome, &amp; the seates well placed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They must sit neere to the doore, and must admonishe those
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151078:30"/>that come, to signe their names in the table of those that frequent, and those (besides) that wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, to signe their names in the table for that purpose. Let them also procure that all take their places as they come, close one to another, that when others come, they may finde empty pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, without stirringe, &amp; mouinge for euery one that comes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They must haue a care that none enter into the <hi>Congregation</hi> that are not of it, vnles they haue particuler leaue of the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> that none enter armed: And if sometime any stranger should insinuate himself, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the <hi>Oratory</hi> to see what is done therein; It is the care of the <hi>Porters</hi> (hauing regard to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the person) in good fashion to aduise him that he goe forthe, or else to dissemble sor one only time. &amp; let him alone, (especially if he be a Prelate, or Gentilman
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151078:30"/>of accounte; &amp; there be no secret busines to be treated in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> or action to be done, at the which straungers presence would be disconuenient) But, if the same partie should continue to come; It is the custome that the <hi>Porters</hi> tell him the second time freely, but withall modestly that it please him to retire him self thence, or else to demaund licence of the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> to remaine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let them note all those that shall haue come to euery <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and those, that shall at anie time be wantinge (acordinge to the Table) geuinge afterwards the said note vnto the <hi>Father,</hi> to the end he may aiwaies knowe truly who hath frequēted, when, &amp; howe ofte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151078:31"/>
            <head>Rules of the Readers.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>LEt him to whome (by turne) it apperteyneth to reade, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to come betime, &amp; about one quarter of an howre before the time assigned for Masse (though the nomber of the assembled be small) let him beginne to reade in that booke, &amp; with that order that the father shal haue assigned, &amp; let him cōtinue on till the <hi>Priest</hi> come forth to say Masse: And if he shall see, that after Masse there be some hinderance for the other exercises, let him reade againe till such time as they beginne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let him endeuour to reade readily, distinctly, &amp; with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible voyce, and let him sit where euery one may easily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When he shalbe hindered to come, let him geue notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151078:31"/>to one of the other <hi>Readers,</hi> that he may supplie for him, and also, when the others shall marke that he to whome it apperteyneth is wantinge, let them procure to supplie them selues accordinge to the order assigned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let him that readeth, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to lay afterwards the booke in his place, &amp; note where he lefte readinge, that it may be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards orderly continued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <head>Rules of those that visite the Sicke.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>SO soone as they shal knowe that any of the <hi>Congregation</hi> be sick, let them endeuour (with all diligence) to goe &amp; visite them, &amp; when they shall see that the sick receaue content, &amp; comforte by their visite, let them visit them oftener. Let them also be diligent
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151078:32"/>in relatinge vnto the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Presect,</hi> the state of the sick, not only the first time, but others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, (especially when they shalbe in daunger of death) since that on this their diligence dependeth, that the said <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefecte,</hi> may ordeyne prayer to be made for their corporall, &amp; spiritual health as also suffrages, when death suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth: Neither is it necessary that the office of visitinge, be done in one, &amp; the self same time, of all the visitours, but two at a time wilbe sufficient, and when that cannot be, one only, &amp; so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, they may better supplie the visites when there shalbe more sick.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151078:32"/>
            <head>CVSTOMES Of the Congregation, <hi>About the gouernement, &amp; the officeres of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that principally gouerneth, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> (especially in spirituall thinges) is one of the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Societie of <hi>Iesus;</hi> After him, the <hi>Prefect</hi> hath the first place, who must be one of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> either an ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall person or lay-man.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>Prefect</hi> are appointed two <hi>Assistants,</hi> vnto which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly followeth the <hi>Secretatie</hi> of the <hi>Cōgregatiō,</hi> who hath an vnder-<hi>Secretarte,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:151078:33"/>that supplieth in all thinges for him whē he is absent.</p>
            <p>All the foresaid fiue are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to sit on the benche of the Magistrates.</p>
            <p>There are besides these other officers following (which may be increased, or doubled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the nomber of the <hi>Soda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi>) 6. <hi>Consultours,</hi> 2. <hi>Sacristans,</hi> one <hi>Treasourer,</hi> 2: <hi>Porters,</hi> 2. <hi>Readers, &amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Visitours</hi> of the <hi>Sick</hi> of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Prefect</hi> is wantinge, or is hindered for some short ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, so that he cannot be present at the <hi>Congregation,</hi> the first <hi>Assistant</hi> gouerneth in his place, &amp; when the first <hi>Assistant</hi> is wantinge, the second supplieth: And though it seldome happen, that all be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge when there is neede; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles (when it shall so happē) the <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Congregation</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wantinge. But when it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth that the <hi>Prefect</hi> departeth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151078:33"/>(not to returne with in the time of his office, or is to haue some long ympedimente so that he cannot be present at the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> at times appointed) then the whole <hi>Congregation</hi> proceedeth to make choyce of another in his place, &amp; the same is to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued touchinge the two <hi>Assistants.</hi> Other Officers are substituted by the particular <hi>Congregation</hi> only, accordinge to necessitie &amp; occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>About the choyce of Officers.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 2.</head>
            <p>THe election of officers is made thrice a yeare (to wit) about the Feastes of the <hi>Conception, Anuntiation,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Assumption</hi> of the glorious Virgin: The <hi>Prefect</hi> &amp; the 2. <hi>Assistants</hi> are chosē by the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>Congregation;</hi> The other officers by the particular <hi>Congregatiō</hi> only, who (as is supposed) hath more
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151078:34"/>distincte, and more intrinsecall knowledge of all in the <hi>Sodalitie:</hi> And all is done after the manner followinge.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Congregation</hi> which goeth before the day appointed for the election of the <hi>Prefect,</hi> &amp; the 2. <hi>Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> notice is geuen of the said future, election, &amp; the names of all that haue actiue, and passiue voyces are read by the <hi>Secretarie,</hi> to renewe by that meanes the memory of all: In the same <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio</hi> also is read all this chapter cōcerninge the electiō of officers.</p>
            <p>Afterwards on the day it self of election, Masse being said, with the prayer of the holy ghoste, and immediatly before the election, the ordinary pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Letanies of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect,</hi> with some shorte discourse, exhorteth all to proceede in the election with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any worldly passion, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge only the glory, and seruice
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151078:34"/>of God, and the spirituall good of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then is said the hymne <hi>Veni Creator Spiritus</hi> with the prayer <hi>Deui qui corda Fidelium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which, in certeine litle papers prepared for that effect by the <hi>Secretary,</hi> with other necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to write, euery one writeth the name only of the persō who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he chooseth for future <hi>Prefect,</hi> he foldes it, and presentes it at the benche before the <hi>Father,</hi> who, together with the <hi>Prefect,</hi> compareth first the nomber of all the suffrages, with the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the assembled, to see how the names giuen in and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that are to giue their voyces do agree, he readeth afterwards to the hearing of all, the suffrages: and the <hi>Secretarie</hi> hath care to note the names of them that are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen, and the nomber of suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as they are geuen to euery one.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:151078:35"/>
            <p> This scrutinie beinge ended, he that hath more then half the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages, is by the <hi>Father,</hi> declared newe <hi>Prefect</hi> of the <hi>Corgregation,</hi> &amp; being led betwene two of the <hi>Sacristans,</hi> after a litle prayer made before the Altar, he is placed in one of the Chayers (prepared by thē for that purpose) in the midst of the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> (to wit) in that which is the midle of the three, &amp; this done, they are to proceede to the election of the two <hi>Assistants</hi> in the like manner.</p>
            <p>Afther this, the <hi>Prefect,</hi> and 2. <hi>Assistants</hi> that haue ended their offices, one after the other, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge in the midst of the <hi>Oratorie</hi> before the <hi>Father,</hi> accuse them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues openly of their faultes cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in their gouernement and humbly demaundinge penance, receaue frō the father that which is geuen them, not returninge any more to the benche.</p>
            <p>This done, <hi>Te Deum Laudamus</hi> is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151078:35"/>said, with the prayer <hi>Deus cuius misericordia,</hi> &amp; the reste of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> departed, to sauinge the <hi>Prefectt,</hi> the <hi>Assistāts</hi> newly chosen, the former <hi>Prefect,</hi> &amp; <hi>Assistants,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the rest of the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Congregation,</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> who chuse the other officers, accordinge to the order as they are before named, and obseruinge that which hereafter shalbe said: &amp; the suffrages are in like manner noted by the <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Cougregation</hi> followinge, the <hi>Prefect,</hi> &amp; the 2. newe <hi>Assistants,</hi> after Masse, and the accustomed prayers, &amp; Letanies, goe to sit on the benche in place of those who ended, &amp; the <hi>Prefect,</hi> or <hi>Father</hi> at his request, saieth briefly some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for edification, before any other exercise beginne.</p>
            <p>The same day, the old <hi>Secretarie</hi> publisheth by wordeof mouth the officers newly chosen, &amp; the old accuse thēselues in like mān<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151078:36"/>before the <hi>Father,</hi> of their faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; receaue penaunces.</p>
            <p>Finally the old <hi>Secretarie</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, or causeth to be read the common Rules of the <hi>Congregation</hi> (in case the <hi>Father</hi> iudgeth it not expedient to deferre it till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time) and the said <hi>Father</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth all to the entire obseruā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of them, notinge some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer thinge wherein defecte is seene.</p>
            <p>Hauinge thus proceeded the oulde <hi>Secretarie</hi> yealdeth his place to the newe, and goeth to accuse himself, &amp; receate penaunce, as the other officers haue done.</p>
            <p>The election of the <hi>Prefect,</hi> and the 2. <hi>Assistants,</hi> is alwaies made by scrutinie, with the greater parte of the voyces of those which are present in <hi>Congregation,</hi> so as they are to exceede the half (as before hath beene said) And when in the first scrutinie there falles out equall voyces betwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151078:36"/>two then they procede to the second in which no other can be chosen then one of those be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene whome the equalitie fell in the precedent scrutinie; And in case they fall equall agai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in nomber of suffrages, lotts are cast, and he is chosen whose name is drawne out: But if in the first scrutinie those that concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re were more then two by equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of voyces, they are to be brought to two only, by a newe scrutinie, or by billets or ballot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, which not succeedinge, they afterwards cast lotts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the two concurrences: the election of the other officers, is made either by scrutinie, or word of mouth, as it best plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the particuler <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Prefect,</hi> &amp; <hi>Assistants,</hi> are not wonte to be confirmed in their offices aboue once only, the same is to be obserued for the most parte in the other officers,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151078:37"/>exceptinge these in whose offices more particuler, &amp; long practise is required, as are the <hi>Secretarte,</hi> of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> the <hi>Sacristans,</hi> and the <hi>Treasourer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Except the <hi>Prefect,</hi> (and when the nomber is great) the <hi>Assistants</hi> also, &amp; <hi>Secretarie</hi> of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> more offices may concurre in one &amp; the self same person, so the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces them selues be not contrary.</p>
            <p>No man in what soeuer electiō hath more then one voyce, no not the <hi>Father,</hi> nor <hi>Prefect</hi> himself.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>About the daies on which the Congregation is held.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 3.</head>
            <p>BEsides the dayes appointed in the Rules, (which are the Saterdayes, &amp; Sundayes of all the yeare, all the Feastes of our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> &amp; of our <hi>B. Lady</hi> (of precept)
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151078:37"/>the feasts of the holy Apostles that fall vpon wensday, &amp; the Feastes of all Sainctes, the <hi>Congregation</hi> is to be held on other dayes also for diuers occasions, either on the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Feast of the <hi>Congregation</hi> or the offices of the Holy weeke.</p>
            <p>For the better solemnizinge their proper Feast, which is that of the <hi>Immaculate Conception</hi> of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> they are wont to assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them selues together for 8. dayes before the said Feast; euery morninge to heare Masse; to say the Letanies of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> and to make a quarter of an hower of mentall prayer vpon thes pointes which the <hi>Father</hi> proposeth: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they must assemble thēselues also on the Eue to say Vesperas.</p>
            <p>To celebrate the offices of the Holy weeke, they must assemble themselues the 3. dayes in which they are said, as well in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge as the morninge, &amp; further, on holy thursday morninge, for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151078:38"/>Masse &amp; communicate in the said <hi>Oratorie,</hi> &amp; for the cōference vpon the <hi>B. Sacramente;</hi> After which, they are wonte to goe into the Churche, to attend on the most holy <hi>Body</hi> of our Lord to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher: And on holy Saterday morninge (besides the howers which are first said) there are read also the prophecies, &amp; Masse fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing at which it is fit al shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be present: To the prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>B. Sacramen</hi> in the <hi>Oratorie</hi> for the necessities of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, they also assemble themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues the day appointed, accordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to the maner conteyned in the customes about the <hi>quarant-hower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Easter</hi> Sunday (by reason of the bond which euery Christian hath to cōmunicate in his proper parishe) there is no <hi>Congregation;</hi> Neither in the twoe other feastes which ymediatly followe, to the ende they may attende to their other deuotiōs; And for the same
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151078:38"/>reason there is wonte to be no <hi>Congregation</hi> on Christmas day.</p>
            <p>It is likewise omitted whē for any publique solemnitie, all, or the greater parte of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> are likely to be hindered, or for other reasonable causes as the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Prefect</hi> shall iudge, geuing warning thereof, that all may knowe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>About the Particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 4.</head>
            <p>ON the first Saterday of euery moneth, &amp; euery other time that there occurreth any vrgent necessitie, there is a Particuler <hi>Congregation</hi> imediatly helde after the General &amp; the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect</hi> vse to geue notice thereof.</p>
            <p>At this Particular <hi>Congregation</hi> there vseth ordinarily to be presēt the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Prefect,</hi> the 2. <hi>Assistāes,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:151078:39"/>the <hi>Secretary</hi> &amp; the <hi>Consultours</hi> only, Neuertheles sometimes also other officers, &amp; others (not officers) are wont to be called, according to the matters which are to bee treated, as the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Prefect</hi> shall thincke good,</p>
            <p>The order that is to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued is that which followeth first, are said a <hi>Patur noster,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> with the prayer <hi>Actiones nostras:</hi> Secondly, the thinges to be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, are proposed, &amp; euery one to propose that which to him oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth, for the seruice, and good of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> lastly the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> ended with an <hi>Aue Maries stella</hi> &amp; the prayer <hi>Defende quaesumus Domine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first that speaketh his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion about that which is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, is the <hi>Prefect,</hi> After whome followe the first &amp; secōd <hi>Assistants,</hi> the <hi>Secretarie,</hi> and so the rest one after another, and all are to be secret.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:151078:39"/>
            <p> Of the thinges that are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the particuler <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> apperteyninge vnto all; Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be geuē to the rest in the next Generall <hi>Congregation,</hi> to the end those thinges may be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingely performed: And the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary</hi> as he hath care to set dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne all in the booke of <hi>Actes,</hi> of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> so is it his care also to remember the <hi>Father</hi> &amp; <hi>Prefect</hi> to doe the foresaid office in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>About the ordinary Exercises of the Congregation.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 5.</head>
            <p>THe ordinary exercises of the <hi>Congregation</hi> are these follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge.</p>
            <p>First, some spiritual booke is read for a quarter of an hower while they come together.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151078:40"/>
            <p> Secondly, Masse is said.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if it be not necessary to resume the spirituall readinge for some occurrence, the <hi>Father,</hi> or some other Priest say the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers before the <hi>Congregation,</hi> with the Letanies of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> all answeringe thereunto.</p>
            <p>Fowerthly, some pointes of meditation are briefly proposed by the <hi>Father,</hi> whereupon all doe afterwards meditate for one quarter of an hower in silence.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, At the end of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the <hi>Father</hi> is wonte to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commende to theire prayers, some particuler occurrence, or necessitie.</p>
            <p>Sextly, The rest of the time is spent in some spirituall exercise, which accordinge to the dayes is chaunged.</p>
            <p>Seauently, The exercise to be done in the next <hi>Congregation,</hi> and other such like thinges are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:151078:40"/>
            <p> Eghtly, The letters directed to the <hi>Congregation</hi> (when any come) are read.</p>
            <p>Nintly, If any be to enter, they are then admitted.</p>
            <p>Tently, The <hi>Secretarie</hi> readeth, or causeth to be read the <hi>Indulgēce</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which they may gaine for that weeke, by sayinge seauen times the <hi>Paternosters,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> in some Churche of those of the <hi>Societie</hi> of <hi>Iesus,</hi> or in others (when in the place where they are, there be no <hi>Churches</hi> of the said <hi>Societie.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Eleuently, The prayers of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> are said by the <hi>Father,</hi> or some other Prieste.</p>
            <p>Twelftly, One other Masse is said for those who were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the first.</p>
            <p>On euery Sunday, &amp; certeine other feastes also, a conference is wonte to be made of some moral pointes, after the manner which more fully is afterwards said in the particuler Chapter thereof.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:151078:41"/>
            <p> On the Saterday before the first Sunday of the moneth followin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge when it may be, &amp; that there is time, the Father is wont to geue some notice vnto all of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Communion, which is to be made on the said first Sunday.</p>
            <p>Euery moneth a Masse is to be said by some Priest of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> appointed by the <hi>Prefecte:</hi> And the first Saterday of the moneth euery one is to heare a Masse, and one Nocturne, &amp; three lessons of the office of the dead is to be said for the soules departed of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> in generall, in the <hi>Oratory;</hi> And before it beginneth, the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary</hi> readeth, or causeth to be read the names of those of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalitie</hi> deceased.</p>
            <p>On the 2. Saterday of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth 3. appointed and warned by the <hi>Father,</hi> are to discourse vpon the <hi>Saincte,</hi> sentence, and vertue, which befalleth the <hi>Congregation,</hi> in common, when the distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151078:41"/>of Sainctes is made: The first speaketh of the Saincte; the second of the vertue; the third of the sentence.</p>
            <p>On the 3. Saterday there is no determinate exercise besides the foresaid, nor on the fouerth when the moneth chaunceth to haue fiue.</p>
            <p>On the last Saterday is wont to be made the distributiō of <hi>Sainctes,</hi> with the other thinges which that action requireth, as is more fully said in his particuler chapter.</p>
            <p>On the feastes of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> of all <hi>Sainctes,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> there is no determinate exercise, neither of discourse, nor conferēce: But the <hi>Father</hi> is wont to see, &amp; deliberate what maketh most to the purpose.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>B. Sacrament</hi> is expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, an exhortation is made after Masse.</p>
            <p>On the day of the <hi>Immaculate Conception</hi> in the morninge, Masse
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151078:42"/>is said by the <hi>Father,</hi> or some other Priest; There is a generall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniō to the which all men may be admitted; Afterwards are said the wonted prayers, with the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanies of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> &amp; imediatly followeth a Sermon, and when there remayneth time there are said other Masses.</p>
            <p>On the Saterday with in the Octaue of the commemoration of the Dead, a Masse of <hi>Requiem</hi> is said, and afterwards, the whole office of the dead, for them of the <hi>Congregation</hi> deceased; And the prayers wonte to be said before, &amp; after the <hi>Congregation,</hi> the Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and the meditation are omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which likewise is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, when the whole office of the dead is said for any one of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> departed.</p>
            <p>On the dayes that the Election of officers is made, there is no meditation, nor other exercise, but that is obserued which is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151078:42"/>afore said in his particuler Chapt.</p>
            <p>On the day that the newe <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> taketh possession, or on some other that the <hi>Father</hi> thincketh good, in place of the forenamed spirituall exercise after the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, are wonte to be read the common Rules of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Of Masses.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 6.</head>
            <p>THe Masse is wont to be said at the beginninge of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> &amp; it beginneth alwaies at the hower which from time to time the <hi>Father</hi> doth appointe, without missinge any whit, that so the other exercises may haue their due time.</p>
            <p>Another Masse also is to be said after the <hi>Congregation</hi> for those which haue denotion to heare it.</p>
            <p>Al are wonte to be admonished precisely of the hower of Masse (as well in winter as in somer)
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151078:43"/>to the end that knowinge it, they may distribute pūctually the time for other thinges.</p>
            <p>Vpon holy thursday Masse is said in the <hi>Oratorie,</hi> where there is a generall Communion, with a conference of the <hi>B Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon Easter eue Masse is said with the Prophecies, &amp; Letanies.</p>
            <p>When any of the <hi>Congregation</hi> should happen to be made Priest, it must be signified vnto the <hi>Father</hi> that he may inuite the rest to heare his first Masse, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate (if they will) thereat; And at the end they kisse (for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence sake) his hand, And if time permit, they are wonte to make a conference of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie &amp; dignitie of Priest hoode; of the reuerenee which is due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priestes, and of the vertues which they ought to haue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:151078:43"/>
            <head>Of the holy Communion</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 7.</head>
            <p>WHen any (for some necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impediment) cometh not in time for to communicate with the rest at the first Masse, let him deferre it vntill the last, not to trouble the exercises of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Oratorie</hi> there is wont ordinarily to be a <hi>Father</hi> (vntill the time of the communion) for the commoditie of those which haue neede to confesse.</p>
            <p>The time of cōmunion is after the Priest hath cōmunicated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, before he taketh ablution.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Of Praier &amp; Meditation.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 8.</head>
            <p>THe Meditation ordinarily is not to be omitted whā there is a <hi>Congregation,</hi> except on those
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151078:44"/>dayes in the which the election of officers is made; the office of the dead is said with three Noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes and when the <hi>B. Sacrament</hi> is exposed.</p>
            <p>For the Meditation, the <hi>Father</hi> is briefly to propose the matter, &amp; those pointes which he shall iudge to be most to the purpose; which sometimes he causeth to be read out of soome booke.</p>
            <p>The Meditation doth not last aboue a quarter of an hower, and it is to be made after the letanies of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> before all other spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall exercises: And before they beginne, the <hi>Father,</hi> (after the pointes be geuen) or some other Priest, is wont to say the prayer <hi>Actiones nostras &amp;c.</hi> &amp; in the ende to beginne the <hi>Magnificat,</hi> standinge &amp; the rest say forwards by turnes, some on the one side, &amp; some on the other, &amp; after all, he sayeth the prayer <hi>Famulis tuis quaesumus Domine.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:151078:44"/>
            <head>Of the Conferences.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 9.</head>
            <p>THe Conferences are to be made ordinarily vpon all the Sundayes in the yeare, vpon the Gospells which occurre, and at any other time when the <hi>Father</hi> shall thinke good vpon the same matters of the Gospells occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or others,</p>
            <p>It belongeth to the <hi>Father</hi> to aske them indifferētly as he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes good, but he taketh heede not to aske but such as will take it in good parte.</p>
            <p>If vnto those which the <hi>Father</hi> doth aske, nothinge doe occurre, It is sufficient, that puttinge of their hats they answere modestly that nothinge doth occurre vnto them; but when they would say any thinge, puttinge on their hatts lett them doe it aloude that they may be vnderstood by all, &amp; the <hi>Father</hi> may now &amp; then briefly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151078:45"/>enterlace some thinge betwene euery ones discourse.</p>
            <p>In this exercise of the <hi>Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> ostentation is to be shunned, &amp; prolixitie, that others may haue time to speake, &amp; they must auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de speculatiue discourse, &amp; with breuitye, and simplicitie attend vnto morall, &amp; practicall conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, by the which they may receaue profite, which in all is the ende of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> but particulerly in this conference.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the Praier of quarant-hower.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 10.</head>
            <p>WHen the <hi>B. Sacrament</hi> is to be exposed in the <hi>Oratory</hi> vpō the day appointed, the Altar and the <hi>Oratory,</hi> is decently to be ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but in such māner, that ostē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, &amp; superfluitie be shūned,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151078:45"/>&amp; yet that nothinge be wantinge vnto the conuenient adorning of the same: And for this cause in particuler there must not be more then 24. lightes of white waxe placed with proportion.</p>
            <p>That morninge Masse is to be said, &amp; a generall communion is made thereat: And when there is commoditie for musick, some mottet may be sunge at the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory at the eleuation, &amp; in time of the generall Communion.</p>
            <p>Masse beinge done, ymediatly (without loosinge of time) the letanies of our <hi>B. Lady</hi> are read by him that hath said the Masse, kneelinge before the Altar, &amp; all answere deuoutly, &amp; after hauing incensed the <hi>B. Sacrament,</hi> he set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it in the place prepared.</p>
            <p>After which there is a Sermon of half an hower, which ended, accordinge to the bill which is set vp neere vnto the doore of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> one after another all that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151078:46"/>day they make their determinate howers of prayer, and sometime after dinner, the <hi>Father,</hi> or some body else maketh another Sermō</p>
            <p>Moreouer when they haue cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditye, nowe &amp; then some mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, psalme, or other spirituall thinge may be sunge with a fewe, good and sweete voyces, which may helpe deuotion.</p>
            <p>The same eueninge without other ceremonie, or solemnitie the <hi>B. Sacrament</hi> is couered vpon the Altar of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> the which afterwards is carried back into the Churche by the <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the Distribution of the Sainctes of euery moneth.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 11.</head>
            <p>VPon the last Saterday of euery moneth Sainctes are distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted for the moneth followin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151078:46"/>The which is done with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine litle papers prepared by the <hi>Sacristans</hi> against that day in suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient nomber: Euery one of which papers is to haue the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the <hi>Saincte,</hi> and the day of the Feast; a spirituall sentence, with a vertue vnto which they are especially, to attende; a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer intention and the name of one of the <hi>Sodalitie</hi> to pray for: The manner to be obserued in the distributing of these <hi>Sainctes,</hi> is as followeth.</p>
            <p>At the time appointed <hi>Vent Creator spititus</hi> being said with the prayer <hi>Deus qui corda Fidelium,</hi> All remayninge vppon their knees, the <hi>Father</hi> at the Altar draweth a paper, and the <hi>Saincte</hi> therein contained, is to be the next moneth followinge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour of the whole <hi>Congregation,</hi> he readeth it publiquely, and all make a litle short prayer geuinge thanckes vnto the <hi>Saincte</hi> of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151078:47"/>moneth past for, the protection which he hath had of the <hi>Sodalitie,</hi> &amp; intreating the newe one to take the protection of it in place of the other; Then risinge vp, they sit downe; The <hi>Father</hi> taketh a <hi>Saincte</hi> for himself, &amp; readeth the paper after the same manner; Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the <hi>Prefect,</hi> the first, and second <hi>Assistants,</hi> the <hi>Secretarie,</hi> and after, all the rest accordinge as they are called by the <hi>Secretarie,</hi> &amp; euery one whilest the <hi>Father</hi> doth reade his <hi>Saincte,</hi> kneeles on the ground bare headed before the Altar, and hauing receaued the <hi>Saincte</hi> at the hand of the <hi>Father,</hi> he maketh a short prayer applyinge vnto his owne <hi>Saincte,</hi> and vnto himself in particuler that which is said before of the whole <hi>Soda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The distribution being ended, the letanies of the <hi>Sainctes</hi> are said, puttinge the name of the <hi>Saincte</hi> which hath hapned vnto the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151078:47"/>whole <hi>Sodalitie</hi> in his proper place therein, and repeatinge it twice: And after the letanies, the prayer <hi>Concede quaesumus omnipotens Deus vt intercessio &amp;c.</hi> is said.</p>
            <p>The paper of the <hi>Saincte</hi> which hath hapned to the whole <hi>Sodali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> is by the <hi>Secretarie</hi> placed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all may whensoeuer they will see it, &amp; reade it: And on the same day those three are admonished, who the time appointed are to make some discourse vpon the <hi>Saincte,</hi> the sentence &amp; the vertue.</p>
            <p>Vnto those which were not present at the distribution, (that they be not depriued of so great a good,) the papers of the <hi>Sainctes</hi> are geuen after, without any other ceremonie.</p>
            <p>Whilest the distribution of the <hi>Sainctes</hi> is made, all must attende with diligence vnto the spirituall sentences which are read procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe to receaue profite thereby.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:151078:48"/>
            <head>Of the visitinge of Hospitalls.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 12.</head>
            <p>ORdinarily vppon all the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes of the yeare when they are not hindered by some other exercise in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> or by some other more vrgent occasiō, they are wont to goe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge in competent numbers, &amp; the <hi>Father</hi> with thē, to visite some <hi>Hospitall</hi> &amp; to serue the sick in time of dinner, taking also occasion to geue them some spirituall repaste of good counsaile, that so cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie be exercised not only with their bodies, but also with their soules, in that half hower, or litle more, which is bestowed therein. They goe thither (of themselues) without obligation of meetinge in any other place (except in the said hospitall) And, (besides, some which are accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to goe ordinarily of their owne accord) It is the vse that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151078:48"/>others be particulerly in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique <hi>Congregatiō</hi> inuited vnto that exercise the sunday before, for the Friday followinge, who (hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe themselues named) vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their heads, in token that they doe accepte the inuitation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the spirituall Offeringes.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 13.</head>
            <p>THey are wont to make some spirituall offeringes vnto God vnto our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> &amp; vnto the <hi>Sainctes;</hi> The which do consiste in fastinges, disciplininges, and communions, visitinge of Hospi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, of the prisoners, hearinge Masse, in almes, visitinge Holy places, the Rosarie, the beades, sayinge some office, vocall and mentall prayer, actes of vertue, &amp; other workes of pietie, either for the whole moneth, weeke, or one day only, as euery one shall thinke best.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151078:49"/>
            <p> These offerings are wonte to be made vppon the dayes which the <hi>Father</hi> doth assigne, and vppon occasion, of some feast followin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge; as of the <hi>Conception</hi> of the most <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> of all <hi>Sainctes,</hi> of <hi>Aduent,</hi> of the <hi>Epiphanie,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Anuntiation,</hi> on which (being the day our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> beganne) an annuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is made) with thanckesge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, vnto God, &amp; vnto his most holy Mother; &amp; in acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of so greeat a fauour, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mewhat is offered vnto them, of our pouerty, chiefly on that day, when the <hi>Sonne</hi> of God became man for our sake; And they must pray for the happie progresse, &amp; spirituall aduauncement of the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alwaies when they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand of any trouble, or vrgēt necessitie of the Christian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthe, (especially of our Countrey) like offeringes are made vnto our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> to his most
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151078:49"/>Holy Mother, &amp; vnto the <hi>Sainctes,</hi> that they would mitigate the wrath of Almightie God and be our Patrons, and Intercessours in those necessities.</p>
            <p>The foresaid offeringes are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in writtinge, &amp; the wordes, &amp; intention is such, that they are not helde for vowes, but only for deuoute purposes, by the neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge whereof they commit no sinne, but only the merite is lost which was to be had for that good worke: And in the bill is written the name and surname of him which offers it, the which bill they bringe from home rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die made, or else they write it in the <hi>Oratorie</hi> it self in papers, which for that purpose are prepared, reteyninge with them a copie for their memorie; Afterwards euery one (as he sits in the <hi>Oratory</hi>) goeth to carrie his bil to the boxe, for this purpose placed at the foote of the Crucifixe before the Altar
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151078:50"/>kissinge first the foote of the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe: And these billes come not to the hands of others, but of the <hi>Father</hi> only, who burneth them; And the memory of that which is conteyned in them serueth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the spirituall good of the offerour.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>Of Candelmasse &amp; Palme Sunday.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 14.</head>
            <p>VPon Candelmas day &amp; Palme Sunday, the <hi>Father,</hi> or some other Prieste, blesseth the cādles, &amp; Palmes, which are prouided, of the same fashion, &amp; bignes for all.</p>
            <p>The distribution of the same is made afterwards amongst all the <hi>Congregation</hi> which are present in the <hi>Oratory;</hi> first vnto the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> then vnto the <hi>Prefect,</hi> &amp; the rest of the Officers which sit vpō
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151078:50"/>the Benche and afterwards vnto the others, beginninge in order from the top of the benche.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sacristans</hi> haue care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide candels for that day &amp; bowes of oliues with litle crosses of pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the accusinge themselues of their owne faults.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 15.</head>
            <p>IT is the custome nowe &amp; then of some more feruēte to accuse themselues publiquely of their faultes and defectes committed in the obseruinge of the Rules &amp; the like, &amp; kneelinge downe before the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Prefect,</hi> they humbly aske penaunce in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, which the <hi>Father</hi> geueth thē. In these actions, (besides that they geue edification vnto others, and become more exact obseruers of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151078:51"/>the Rules) they merite very much before Almighty God; The fittest time for their accusation, is after the meditation, and before the Conference beginne.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>The manner of cominge in, &amp; goinge out of the Oratorie.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 16.</head>
            <p>ALl at their entringe in to the <hi>Oratory,</hi> first take holy water, &amp; then signe their names in the Table of those that frequent: And those that will communicate doe signe their names in the Table of communicantes, to the ende that the <hi>Sacristans</hi> may knowe the nō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of those which are to cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, &amp; may prouide sufficient hostes. This beinge done, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge on both knees, they make a litle prayer as long as they thincke good, soo that the exercise be not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151078:51"/>begunne. But cominge in time of meditation, they meditate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the rest; And if they come whilest the pointes of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation are geuinge, or in time of conference, of sermon, or exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, It is sufficient they kneele downe, &amp; make a short prayer, &amp; after reuerēce made to the Altar, they turne themselues likewise to those that sit vpon the benches, &amp; it is sufficient that the <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Prefect</hi> vncouer vnto thē, to auoyde disturbance, Then they sit downe in a place, in which they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seene comodiously procuringe to sit close (as much as they can) to leaue place for others.</p>
            <p>In sittinge, the 26. common Rule is exactly obserued, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge without ceremonie, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence: Chayers are only geuen to the <hi>Father</hi> &amp; Magistrates.</p>
            <p>In goinge forth, they obserue the same, without hauing any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respect of Precidēcie, the which is
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151078:52"/>alwaies cause of disunion, and disagreeinge of opinion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>Of the manner of admittinge into the Sodality.</head>
            <head type="sub">CHAPTER 17.</head>
            <p>IN the memorialls which they do giue vp that desire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, they are to write their names, surnames, countrey, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and dwellinge place, and whē the persons are not knowne the diligēce is obserued, which is set downe in the cōmon Rule 31.</p>
            <p>After they are receaued to the Probation, they vse in the 3. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes of it, to be present at all the spirituall exercises which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily are performed, to the end, that by their proceedinge they may be knowne, &amp; a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made of them; and on the other side, they seeinge that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151078:52"/>which others doe, learne the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruance of the Rules, but they are not permitted to haue suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in the election, or admission, or any other busenes which is treated of in the <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time of their Probation being expired, their <hi>Instructours</hi> doe propounde to the whole <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> their admission (but yet in the absence of those which are to be admitted) &amp; their <hi>Instructours</hi> make the relatiō according to the contētes in their particuler Rules: After the wonted prayers are said (that is <hi>Veni Creator spiritus,</hi> and the prayer of the holy Ghoste) they goe about the choyce, &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parte of the suffrages preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, &amp; if they receaue him, they aduise him by his Instructours of his receauinge, &amp; in the nex <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> they cause him to be brought in by the same <hi>Instructours</hi> &amp; they receaue him with the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed prayers, &amp; ceremonies,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151078:53"/>being met in the entrance by 2. <hi>Sacristans,</hi> and brought betwene thē to kneele downe hard by the Altar, where they make a litle prayer, which being done, the <hi>Sacristans</hi> carry them to the ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, where they are embraced in name of all the <hi>Congregation,</hi> first of the <hi>Father,</hi> then of the <hi>Magistates,</hi> &amp; they put them in minde of the <hi>plenary Indulgence</hi> which they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne: And lastly they say <hi>Te Deum Laudamus,</hi> with the prayer <hi>Da nobis quaesumus Domine perseuerantem &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not the custome to admitt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any of another <hi>Congregatiō</hi> to ours, whose patentes be not very well examined, or at least the person himself, and certeine notice is to be procured whether he haue the qualities required in one of our <hi>Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Prelates are so priuiledged that without any probation, or further triall, it sufficeth they sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Prefect</hi> their
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151078:53"/>desire to enter into the <hi>Congregatiō,</hi> &amp; so to be admitted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instruction">
            <head>The manner of recommendinge himself to God in the Morninge.</head>
            <head type="sub">1.</head>
            <p>TO geue thanckes to Almig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God for the benefites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in generall, &amp; in particuler for hauing passed well that night. 2. To offer himself wholy in the hands of Almighty God, and pray that he keepe him, and geue him grace to doe that day al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges accordinge to his will.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To consider those thinges, which doe most draw him to sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, resoluinge to absteine from them &amp; withall renewinge his good purpose of spirituall life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To aske helpe to that end of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> and to recommend
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151078:54"/>himself to all the companie of the blessed of heauen, and in Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to his Saincte protectour for that moneth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Lastly to say thrice <hi>Pater noster</hi> &amp; thrice <hi>Aue Maria</hi> for all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aliue &amp; dead, &amp; to goe deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Masse offeringe that sacrifice for his sinnes &amp; the necessities of the Holy Churche.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instruction">
            <head>A manner of examininge our Concience at night</head>
            <p>TO giue thanckes to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God for the benefites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued generally, &amp; in particuler for those receaued that day.</p>
            <p>To aske grace of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> &amp; true light to knowe, &amp; hate sinne &amp; in particuler the errours comit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that day.</p>
            <p>To aske accounte of his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all that wherein he shall haue offended Almightie God
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151078:54"/>that day in thought, word, deede and omission, attending to those defects to which he is most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined.</p>
            <p>To aske of almighty God hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pardon of whatsoeuer fault or sinne which he shall finde</p>
            <p>To haue a firme purpose to preserue himself by the helpe of almighty God from sinne here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, with purpose to confesse himself endinge with <hi>Pater noster, Aue Maria</hi> &amp; the <hi>Creede.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:151078:55"/>
            <p>SOme fewe Chapters of the Roman Copie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning certaine particular officers, &amp; some kinde of penaunces, &amp; expences, (not makinge for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent purpose) are in this edition omitted, kept not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandinge by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie to be printed, &amp; practised when it shalbe iudged conuenient.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151078:55"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>